Preliminary Inventory of the Iran Freedom Foundation Records
Hoover Institution Archives
Iran Freedom Foundation Records
1966-1993
93035
Iran Freedom Foundation; Tabatabai, Ali Akbar, 1930-1980
60 manuscript boxes, 3 cassette boxes, 1 open reel box, 2 cubic foot boxes, and 1 oversize box (27.7 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection relates to the Iranian revolution of 1979, subsequent political conditions and civil rights abuses in Iran, the Iran-Iraq War, Iranians in the United States and elsewhere, and American foreign policy toward Iran. It contains correspondence, press releases, appeals, clippings, speeches and writings, financial records, reports, bulletins, newsletters, pamphlets, serial issues, photographs, sound recordings, and videotapes. The collection includes some personal papers, 1966-1980, of Ali A. Tabatabai, founder of the organization, and material relating to his assassination.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1993.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
The Iran Freedom Foundation (IFF) was formed in Bethesda, Maryland in October 1979. Prior to establishing the IFF, the organization's founder and president, Ali Akbar Tabatabai worked as director of the Foreign Relations Department of the Ministry of Information in Tehran and press attaché at the Iranian embassy in Washington, D.C., in the final years of the Shah's reign and under the leadership of Ambassador Ardeshir Zahedi (1977-1979). Ali Akbar Tabatabai was assassinated in July 1980 by Daoud Salahuddin (David Belfield) at the front door of his home in Maryland. After his assassination, Ali Akbar's identical twin brother, Mohammad Reza, took over the operations of the IFF.
The IFF supported a secular democracy in Iran and actively opposed the Islamic fundamentalist regime of Ayatollah Khomeini. Both Ali Akbar and Mohammad Reza frequently appeared on television and radio programs to promote awareness of human rights violations in Iran. In addition, the IFF disseminated information about Iran to members of the U.S. House and Senate as well as to members of the general public who wrote to the foundation with questions about Iran. The foundation worked closely with Iranian nationalist groups overseas, most notably Chapour Bakhtiar's National Movement of Iranian Resistance and Bahram Aryana's Azadegan.
Source:
"Iran Ex-Attaché, Khomeini Foe, Slain in the U.S." New York Times, July 23, 1980
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection relates to the Iranian revolution of 1979, subsequent political conditions and civil rights abuses in Iran, the Iran-Iraq War, Iranians in the United States and elsewhere, and American foreign policy toward Iran. It contains correspondence, press releases, appeals, clippings, speeches and writings, financial records, reports, bulletins, newsletters, pamphlets, serial issues, photographs, sound recordings, and videotapes. The collection includes some personal papers, 1966-1980, of Ali A. Tabatabai, founder of the organization, and material relating to his assassination.
The majority of the collection consists of clippings, subject files, and printed matter relating to political and social events within Iran and surrounding countries, Iranian foreign relations, and the experiences of Iranian émigrés in the United States. Among these materials are volumes of photocopied clippings from Tabatabai's time as press attaché for the Iranian embassy in Washington, D.C., covering the critical months leading up to the establishment of the Islamic Republic of Iran, November 1978 to February 1979. Subject files also contain clippings, press releases, and speeches relating to the assassination of Ali Akbar Tabatabai.
Following Ali Akbar Tabatabai's assassination, the Iran Freedom Foundation held several political rallies from 1981 to 1983 in support of secular democracy in Iran. While subject files contain flyers and speeches from these events, the publicity files include drafts of speeches and writings, press releases, and background information on the foundation's activities.
The Iran Freedom Foundation sponsored one of the first anti-Khomeini Persian-language radio programs in the United States on WLMD radio in Maryland. Referred to as both the Iranian Hour and Iran Freedom Movement radio, the program was used as a forum to disseminate information about Iran and unite Iranian émigrés in the United States. The collection contains recordings of broadcasts as well as radio program materials in the form of notes, research headlines, clippings, and financial records. Sound recordings are identified in the container list by their labels. However, the contents of the sound recordings may not match their labels.
Description of Major Groups
The collection is unarranged, but most materials fall into the following major groups.
1, 3, 5, 9, 11-12, 15, 18, 20, 26, 29-30, 33, 36-38, 40-42, 45, 49, 51, 54 Publicity file, 1979-1984. Includes general background information, press releases, newsletters, bulletins, transcripts, speeches and writings, and notes
1-4, 8-13, 16,18, 20, 28-30, 32, 34, 38-39, 44, 46, 48, 50, 52 Subject file, 1967-1992. Consists of clippings, magazines, collected articles, correspondence, flyers, newsletters, bulletins, speeches, government documents, and writings
1-7, 11, 14, 26-36, 39-41, 44-45, 48-50, 52, 55 Clippings, 1971-1990. Consists of clippings from Iranian, American, and Saudi Arabian newspapers and magazines, mostly in English
1-9, 15-16, 18, 29, 33-34, 37-38, 47-49, 51, 53, 55 56-57 Printed matter, 1978-1993. Consists of newspapers, magazines, monographs, newsletters, and pamphlets
1, 3, 5, 10-11, 13, 15-16, 19, 29-30, 33, 36, 39, 41,48, 50, 56 Correspondence, 1979-1992. Consists mainly of letters sent and received, and enclosures
20-25, 32-33, 42, 48-49, 51 Press attaché of the Iranian embassy, Washington, D.C., materials, 1953, 1970-1979. Consists of memoranda, correspondence, clippings, notes, and photographs
19-20, 26, 40, 42-44 Radio program materials, 1981-1983, undated. Consists of notes, scripts, clippings, press summaries, and financial records relating to a Persian language program radio program in Maryland
8, 11, 16-18, 32, 40, 51 Photographs, 1970-1983, undated. Consists of prints and negatives
58-60 Video recordings, 1979-1981, undated. Contains recordings of interviews on U-matic videocassettes, arranged chronologically by subject
61-66 Sound recordings, 1979-circa 1987, undated. Compact sound cassettes and open reel tapes arranged by form then by title chronologically
67 Oversize materials, 1975-1990. Contains newspapers, posters, flyers, and a calendar
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Civil rights--Iran.; Iran-Iraq War, 1980-1988.; Iran--History--Revolution, 1979.; Iran--Politics and government--1979-1997.; Iran--Emigration and immigration.; Iran--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Iran.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence with White House and U.S. Department of State officials regarding Iran, 1981-1986 (Box 1)
- Clippings and printed matter on Iran, 1979-1987 (Box 1)
- Iranian groups in exile newsletters and announcements, 1987; undated (Box 1)
- Subject file
  - Assassination of A. A. Tabatabai, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Bakhtiar, Chapour, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Iran--General, undated (Box 1)
  - Iran--Pre- and post-revolution, 1979-1982 (Box 1)
  - Islamic Education Center, Washington, D.C., 1983-1985 (Box 1)
  - People's Mojahedin Organization of Iran, 1984-1989 (Box 1)
- Publicity file
  - Transcripts of television and radio appearances, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Iran Freedom Foundation (IFF) newsletters, advertisements, and activity report, 1979-1982 (Box 1)
- Arya, newspaper, 1981 (Box 2)
- Akhbar-i Iran, newspaper, circa 1980 (Box 2)
- Azadegan newsletters, 1981 (Box 2)
- Bakhtiar, Chapour newsletters, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
- Clippings on Iran from American and Saudi Arabian newspapers, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  In English
- Subject file
  - Terrorism, 1980-1984 (Box 2)
  - Persian Gulf, 1967; undated (Box 2)
  - Human rights in Iran, 1980-1982 (Box 3)
  - Iran--History, undated (Box 3)
  - People's Mojahedin Organization of Iran, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - Personal security, 1981 (Box 3)
- Printed matter relating to Iran and Iranian political groups, 1985-1990 (Box 3)
- Clippings, 1979-1984 (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  - General, 1980 (Box 3)
  - White House and U.S. Department of State officials regarding Iran, 1982-1985 (Box 3)
- Publicity file
  - Transcripts of television and radio appearances and other materials, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Directory and mailings, 1980 (Box 3)
- Subject file
  - American hostages in Iran, 1980-1991 (Box 4)
  - Assassination of A. A. Tabatabai, 1980; undated (Box 4)
  - Human rights, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Iranian embassy auction, circa 1980 (Box 4)
  - Khomeini and terrorism, circa 1979-1984 (Box 4)
  - McDonald, Larry P., 1978-1985 (Box 4)
  - Mohtashemi Pour, Ali Akbar, circa 1986 (Box 4)
  - People's Mojahedin Organization of Iran, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Rushdie, Salman. Satanic Verses, 1989 (Box 4)
- Executive Intelligence Review magazine, 1979-1981 (Box 4)
- Middle East People, 1985 (Box 4)
- Clippings and extracts, 1987 (Box 4)
- Publicity file
  - Speech at Iranian Freedom Foundation celebration, 1983 August 4 (Box 4)
  - General background materials and legal records, 1979-1984 (Box 4)
  - M. R. Tabatabai published writings, 1992 (Box 4)
- Correspondence
  - General, 1982-1989 (Box 5)
  - French and American government officials, 1991-1992 (Box 5)
- Press activity, 1984-1985 (Box 5)
- Printed matter
  - Gam, 1987-1990 (Box 5)
  - Human Rights Watch newsletters, 1990-1992 (Box 5)
  - Middle East Watch newsletters, 1990-1993 (Box 5)
  - Clippings on Iran and Iranian émigrés, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - The Washington Post newspapers and clippings, 1979 (Box 6)
  - Iranian groups in exile newsletters and mailings, 1988-1990 (Box 6)
- Events attended, 1989 (Box 6)
- Printed matter and clippings on Iran-Iraq War, Khomeini, and U.S. policy in the Middle East, 1978-1982 (Box 7)
- Photograph of A. A. Tabatabai, undated (Box 8)
- Subject file
  - Afghanistan, 1980 (Box 8)
  - Khomeini and post-revolution analysis, 1980-1982 (Box 8)
- Printed matter
  - Iranian newspapers, 1981 (Box 8)
  - Magazines and newspapers relating to American hostages in Iran, 1980 (Box 8)
  - Iranian groups in exile newsletters, 1980-1984 (Box 9)
  - Iranian newspapers, 1980-1981 (Box 9)
- Subject file
  - Amnesty International, 1981-1983 (Box 9)
  - Bakhtiar, Chapour, undated (Box 9)
  - Iranian Committee for Democratic Action and Human Rights, 1980-1981 (Box 9)
  - Junbish-i Najat-i Iran, 1981 (Box 9)
  - Moslem Students Society, undated (Box 9)
- Publicity file
  - Drafts of advertisements for newspapers, undated (Box 9)
  - Transcripts of television and radio appearances, 1979 November (Box 9)
  - Press releases and statements, 1979-1982 (Box 9)
- Notes and miscellaneous, 1981 (Box 9)
- Pamphlets on Marxism, communist groups in Iran, and Islam, 1977 (Box 9)
- Correspondence
  - General, 1980-1984 (Box 10)
  - Amini, Ali, 1983-1985 (Box 10)
  - U.S. senators and governors, 1980-1984 (Box 10)
- Publicity file
  - Directory of Iranian officials, 1979-1980 (Box 10)
  - Newsletters, press releases, and related materials, 1980-1984 (Box 10)
- Subject file
  - Anjuman-i islami-i danishjuyan dar amrika va kanada, 1985 (Box 10)
  - Anti-Khomeini demonstrations, 1980 (Box 10)
  - Ball, George W., 1981 (Box 10)
  - Banisadr, Abolhasan, 1981 (Box 10)
  - Board of Directors, 1981 (Box 10)
  - Chirik'ha-yi Fada'i-i Khalq-i Iran, 1984 (Box 10)
  - Committee for the Defense of Human Rights in Iran, 1981 (Box 10)
  - Executive Intelligence Review, 1982 (Box 10)
  - Foreign Affairs International, 1982 (Box 10)
  - Guruh-i Vahdat-i Milli-i Iran, 1982 (Box 10)
  - Hizb-i Pan Iranist, 1982 (Box 10)
  - Iran-Sun, 1982 May (Box 10)
  - Jebhe-yi Milliyun Inqilab-i Iran, 1982 (Box 10)
  - Palestinian Liberation Organization (PLO), 1983 (Box 10)
  - Political cartoons, undated (Box 10)
  - Rajai, Mohammad Ali, undated (Box 10)
  - Semkus, Charles Ismail, clippings and correspondence, 1979-1982 (Box 10)
- Legal documents, 1982-1984 (Box 11)
- Subject file (Box 11)
  - Aryana, Bahram, 1981-1982 (Box 11)
  - Immigration and refugees, 1984 (Box 11)
  - Iranian National Unity Organization, 1981-1982 (Box 11)
  - People's Mojahedin Organization of Iran issuances and publications, 1981-1985 (Box 11)
    Includes materials from the Moslem Students Society
- Transcripts from news programs regarding Iran, 1979-1980 (Box 11)
- Publicity file, general, 1979 (Box 11)
- Clippings, 1971-1985 (Box 11)
- Correspondence
  - Copies of cables sent to President Jimmy Carter by IFF, 1979-1980 (Box 11)
  - Arab officials, 1985 (Box 11)
  - Members of U.S. Senate and House of Representatives, 1980-1984 (Box 11)
- Photograph of demonstration and firing squad, undated (Box 11)
- Publicity file
  - Letter from IFF to Saddam Hussein, photocopy, 1983 (Box 12)
  - Letters to the editor, 1981 (Box 12)
  - Drafts of writings, 1982 (Box 12)
- Subject file
  - Anti-Khomeini demonstrations, 1980-1983 (Box 12)
  - Assassination of A. A. Tabatabai, 1980 (Box 12)
    Includes condolence letters
  - People's Mojahedin Organization of Iran, 1981-1985 (Box 12)
  - Women in the Islamic Republic of Iran, undated (Box 12)
  - Anderson, Jack, 1983-1984 (Box 13)
  - Front for the Liberation of Iran newsletters (Box 13)
  - Iranian National Unity Organization newsletters, 1981 (Box 13)
  - Islamic Center, Washington, 1983 (Box 13)
  - Kashm, undated (Box 13)
  - Khoie, Fereydoin and the "Iranian Democratic Party,", 1981 (Box 13)
  - Khomeini, Ayatollah Ruhollah, 1984 (Box 13)
  - Lubbock, Jay Harris, 1979 (Box 13)
  - Mortazavi, Ali, 1980 (Box 13)
  - Payam'ha-yi Hambastegi, 1982 (Box 13)
  - People's Mojahedin Organization of Iran, 1984 (Box 13)
  - Political cartoons, 1981 (Box 13)
  - Sazman-i Avargan-i Iran notes, undated (Box 13)
  - Unification Church, 1982 (Box 13)
- Newsletters and collected materials relating to Iran, 1979-1984 (Box 13)
- Correspondence. Telegrams, 1981 (Box 13)
  Includes several telegrams to President Ronald Reagan after assassination attempt and to Reza Shah II
- Iranian diplomatic passport of A. A. Tabatabai, photocopy, 1979 (Box 13)
- Commentary on hostage crisis, 1980s (Box 13)
- Clippings on Iran from Saudi Arabian newspapers, 1979-1980 (Box 14)
- Assassination of A. A. Tabatabai, 1980 (Box 14)
- Notes and drafts of writings, 1980 (Box 14)
- Correspondence
  - General, 1979-1984 (Box 15)
  - Amini, Ali, 1982-1983 (Box 15)
  - Powell, Diana Kearney, 1981-1983 (Box 15)
  - Semkus, Charles Ismail, 1981-1982 (Box 15)
- Publicity file. Press releases, letters to the editor, and related materials, 1981-1982 (Box 15)
- Printed matter
  - Iranian newspapers, 1981 (Box 15)
  - Executive Intelligence Review and related publications, 1984 (Box 15)
  - Smith, Terence. "Iran: Five Years of Fanaticism" New York Times Magazine, 1983 (Box 15)
  - Gām, 1989-1991 (Box 16)
  - Newspapers and newsletters, 1990-1992 (Box 16)
- Correspondence, 1984-1991 (Box 16)
- Subject file. Immigration and refugees, 1982-1984 (Box 16)
- Photographs
  - Candid shots of gathering at Islamic Center, Washington, D.C., circa 1983 (Box 16)
    Includes negatives
  - Candid shots of gathering at Islamic Center, Washington, D.C., circa 1983 (Box 17)
  - International Day of Quds demonstration, 1982 July 16 (Box 17)
  - Aerial views of Islamic Education Center, circa 1982 (Box 17)
  - Pro-Khomeini demonstrations, circa 1982 (Box 17)
  - Paykar demonstration?, 1982 July 16 (Box 17)
  - Pro-democracy in Iran demonstrations, circa 1983 (Box 17)
  - Fereydoun Farrokhzad concert, 1983 (Box 18)
  - Personal and family, 1960s-1980s (Box 18)
  - Victims of revolutionary fighting in Iran, 1978 (Box 18)
- Printed matter
  - Semkus, Charles Ismail. The Fall of Iran, 1978-1979: An Historical Anthology. New York: Copen Press (Box 18)
  - "Influence of Perceptions of Shia Islam in the U.S.: 1978-1984," student dissertation, undated (Box 18)
- Subject file. Human rights in Iran, 1982 (Box 18)
- Publicity file. General information and plans for nationalist counter-revolution in Iran, 1980 (Box 18)
- Radio program materials, 1981 October-November (Box 19)
  Includes notes, drafts, news clippings, and invoices from a Persian-language radio program on WLMD
- Correspondence
  - Press and media, 1980 (Box 19)
  - Buchanan, Pat and other government officials, 1979-1985 (Box 19)
- Subject file. Anti-khomeini demonstrations, 1982-1983 (Box 20)
- Inspection report, "Contract Administration Services Security Assistance Program, Iran," Office of the Inspector General of Foreign Assistance, 1976 (Box 20)
- Publicity file, general, 1979-1980 (Box 20)
- Institute for International Politics and Economic Studies-Stanford Research Institute "Symposium on Iran in 1980's" conference materials, 1977 October 4-6 (Box 20)
- Printed matter and clippings, circa 1983 (Box 20)
- Revolutionary poems, circa 1979 (Box 20)
- Radio program materials, undated (Box 20)
- Press attaché of the Iranian embassy, Washington, D.C., clippings file, 1979 January (Box 20)
- Press attaché of the Iranian embassy, Washington, D.C., clippings file, 1978 November-1979 February (Box 21-25)
- Publicity file
  - General, 1979-1981 (Box 26)
  - Drafts of speeches and writings by M. R. Tabatabai, undated (Box 26)
- Radio program materials, 1982-1983 (Box 26)
- Clippings and collected materials on terrorism, 1984 (Box 26)
- Clippings, 1982 (Box 27)
- Collected materials on Khomeini, 1979 (Box 27)
- Printed matter. Iranian groups in exile newsletters, 1982 (Box 27)
- Letters of appreciaton for donations, 1980 (Box 27)
- Notebooks and appointment book, 1985; undated (Box 27)
- Subject file. Iran-Iraq War, 1982-1984 (Box 28)
- Publicity file. IFF correspondence, press releases, and other materials, 1979-1983 (Box 28)
- Clippings, 1984 (Box 28)
- Correspondence
  - Helms, Jesse, 1984 (Box 29)
  - Semkus, Charles Ismail, 1978-1979 (Box 29)
- Publicity file. Activity report, 1980 May
- Clippings, 1978-1979 (Box 29)
- Printed matter
  - Aryana, Bahram. Pour Une Ethique Iranienne. Paris: Conti-Fayolle, 1981 (Box 29)
  - Junbish newspaper, 1981-1985 (Box 29)
  - Profile of Iran Special Edition Vol. 2, No. 12, 1978 (Box 29)
    Book published by the Iranian embassy in Washington detailing the relationship between Iran and the United States, released upon the Shah's visit with President Carter
  - Voice of Iran, newspaper, 1984 (Box 29)
- Notes and miscellaneous, undated (Box 29)
- Subject file
  - Radio and television stations in Maryland, 1985 (Box 29)
  - Human rights and socio-political state in Iran, 1979-1980 (Box 29)
  - Congressional pictorial directories, 1981-1983 (Box 29)
  - Afghanistan--Islamic Unity of Afghanistan Mujahideen, 1984 (Box 30)
  - Assassination of A. A. Tabatabai, 1980 (Box 30)
    Includes materials relating to Richard Hirschfield
  - Iran Teacher's Association, 1981-1982 (Box 30)
  - Israel--Sale of arms to Khomeini, 1982 (Box 30)
  - Hostages, 1991; undated (Box 30)
  - Naipaul, V.S. articles, 1981 (Box 30)
- Clippings from The Washington Post related to Pat Buchanan, Middle East politics, the Soviet Union, and United States foreign policy, 1984 (Box 30)
- Correspondence with U.S. Senators and government officials, 1979-1985 (Box 30)
- Publicity file. Letters to the editor, press releases, and speeches, 1979-1984 (Box 30)
- Notes and miscellaneous, 1980; undated (Box 30)
- Alahazrat Reza Shah II clippings, transcripts of speeches, and related materials, 1984-1988 (Box 31)
  See also Sound recordings--Compact sound cassettes
- Clippings on Lebanon, Syria, Egypt, and Israel, 1984 (Box 32)
- Press attaché of the Iranian embassy, Washington, D.C., 1953-1970s
  - General correspondence and memoranda, 1960s-1970s (Box 32)
  - Zahedi, Ardeshir. "Five Decisive Days," drafts, research materials, and printed copy, undated (Box 32)
  - Scrapbooks of clippings and photographs of A. A. Tabatabai in press conferences, 1970 (Box 32)
  - Clippings on coup, 1953 (Box 32)
- Telegrams from A. A. Tabatabai to Mohammad Reza Shah Pahlavi upon his arrival in the U.S., 1979 (Box 32)
- Subject file (Box 32)
  - Iranian history, 1975 (Box 32)
  - Reza Shah II, 1982 (Box 32)
- Printed matter
  - Quarterly Economic Review of Iran, 1977 (Box 33)
  - Reader's Digest, 1980-1985 (Box 33)
- Press attaché of the Iranian embassy, Washington, D.C., correspondence, press contacts, and stationery, 1979 (Box 33)
- Correspondence (Box 33)
  - Aziz, Tariq letter to Secretary General of the United Nations, 1988 (Box 33)
  - Khalatbari, Ali Akbar, 1978 (Box 33)
  - Pakravan, Saideh, 1980 (Box 33)
- Clippings on terrorism, Iran, and U.S. foreign relations, 1983-1988 (Box 33)
- Subject file. Iran-Iraq War, undated (Box 33)
- Publicity file. "U.S. Government Communications and Documents,", 1984 (Box 33)
  Includes copies of cables sent to President Carter and IFF press releases
- Notes and miscellany, undated (Box 33)
- Letters received, general, 1987-1989 (Box 34)
- Clippings and newspapers, 1981 (Box 34)
- Printed matter. Gam, 1987-1988 (Box 34)
- Publicity file. Activity report research materials, 1979-1980 (Box 34)
- Subject file. Anti-Khomeini demonstration materials and speeches, 1980-1982 (Box 34)
- Contacts and mailing lists, undated (Box 35)
- Clippings, 1984 (Box 35)
- Desk calendar and address book, 1980 (Box 35)
- Drafts of speeches on war, oil, terrorism, and Khomeini, 1980 (Box 35)
- Financial records, 1980 (Box 35)
- Letters received, general, 1980-1981 (Box 35)
- A. A. Tabatabai personal file, 1974-1979 (Box 36)
- Subject file. Islamic Education Center, 1985 (Box 36)
- Clippings on Iran and Iraq, 1980-1982 (Box 36)
  Includes correspondence with Charles Ismail Semkus
- Correspondence, 1981-1987 (Box 36)
- Drafts of writings, undated (Box 36)
- Miscellaneous printed matter, 1985 (Box 36)
- Publicity file. Background and press releases, 1979-1980 (Box 36)
- Collected materials and newsletters regarding Iran, Khomeini, the Revolution, human rights, and the Shah, 1979-1984 (Box 37)
- Contract between A. A. Tabatabai and U.S. Joint Publications Research Service, 1979 (Box 37)
- Publicity file
  - Letters to the editor, 1981; 1985 (Box 37)
  - Contacts and mailing lists, 1980 (Box 37)
  - Solicitation for contributions to IFF, 1980 (Box 37)
- Printed matter
  - America's Future, 1980 (Box 37)
  - Vote newsletter, 1980 (Box 37)
  - Pamphlets of excerpts from speeches and interviews with Mohammad Reza Shah Pahlavi, 1976-1977 (Box 38)
  - Iranian groups in exile newsletters and publications, 1987-1990 (Box 38)
  - Al-Jihad magazine, 1993 (Box 38)
- Subject file
  - Assassination of A. A. Tabatabai. Letter to President Bush, 1990 (Box 38)
  - Bakhtiar, Chapour, 1980 (Box 38)
  - Constitutional Councils, U.S. Chapter, 1985 (Box 38)